<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>CVS Guide</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>2003/01/16</date>

    <author>
      <surname>León</surname>

      <firstname>José</firstname>
    </author>

    <author>
      <surname>Kühner</surname>

      <firstname>Jens</firstname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document is intended to provide a brief introduction to CVS,
    it&#39;s recommended you read another tutorials about this matter, there
    are many on the net.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Note: Don&#39;t play with the XPde CVS server, use your
    local system for practice.</emphasis></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>CVS</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>What is CVS?</title>

      <para>CVS is a system for concurrent source code management, it allows
      several developers to work on the same project and also provides version
      control over the source code. The working philosofy is fair simple:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You request the sources from the server</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make your changes to the sources</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Commit the changes to the CVS server</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Then your changes are be available to the rest of the team</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can now delete the project on your system, because the
          real code is stored on the server, not on your machine</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This sounds strange the first time you try, but after that, you
      cannot live without it ;-)</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Checkout</title>

    <para>Checkout is the operation to extract/get the sources from the CVS
    server to make any modification, you just need an anonymous access, follow
    this instructions:</para>

    <programlisting>cvs -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.xpde.berlios.de:/cvsroot/xpde login

cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.xpde.berlios.de:/cvsroot/xpde co xpde</programlisting>

    <para>These commands download the last version of the source code to your
    system, if you look the directories, all of them will have a CVS subdir,
    this subdir contains information for the cvs command about the files
    stored on this directory.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Commit</title>

    <para>After you perform your changes, you must commit them to the server,
    this way, your changes will be available to the rest of the team. You must
    execute this command on the directory you performed the changes.</para>

    <programlisting>cvs commit</programlisting>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Write access</title>

    <para>You cannot commit your changes to the XPde server until you get
    write access to the XPde CVS repository, to get write access to the XPde
    server you will need to be member of the project on BerliOS, subscribe to
    BerliOS as developer and after that, contact with us to add you to the
    project. All the CVS operations are made using SSH, so you need first to
    add the CVS host to your list of trusted hosts:</para>

    <programlisting>ssh cvs.xpde.berlios.de</programlisting>

    <para>And answer yes when prompted.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>gCVS</title>

    <para>You can use a GUI frontend for CVS, is called gCVS, you can download
    it from http://www.wincvs.org/, it&#39;s a GTK application and you must
    configure it following these steps:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the Admin | Preferences menu item</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enter yourberliosuser@cvs.xpde.berlios.de:/cvsroot/xpde on the
        CVSROOT field</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select Secure Shell (ssh) as authetication method</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check also &#34;Run CVS on a terminal (xterm)&#34;, this is done
        this way to allow you enter your password, read below to know how to
        prevent be prompted by a password everytime</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check out the full project using the command Create | Check out
        and entering xpde as the module to check out</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enter your password when prompted, and that&#39;s all ;-)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</article>