<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Readme First</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>2003/01/16</date>

    <author>
      <surname>León</surname>

      <firstname>José</firstname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document is intended to provide all you need to collaborate
    with us in XPde development. This is an open document, so if you feel
    there is something missing, don&#39;t hesitate to contact us.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Your account</title>

    <para>As a part of the team, you will get the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An @xpde.com mail account, you must setup your mail client with
        the following data:</para>

        <para>user: yourlogin%xpde.com</para>

        <para>pass: the one you provided</para>

        <para>POP,SMTP: mail.xpde.com</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>This account will be subscribed to the mailing list
        development@xpde.com, it&#39;s encouraged you read this mail list,
        this is the main method we use for communication, but if you need to
        unsubscribe, send a mail to development-unsubscribe@xpde.com to be
        removed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You also will be added to the Team page, along with your photo,
        your role on the team and a short paragraph about you</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You will be also subscribed to http://dcl.xpde.com, a ticketing
        system we are starting to use to manage the projet, it will be useful
        when the team gets larger</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can also subscribe to http://bugs.xpde.com to report bugs
        and contact with us to update your access level to developer if you
        want to be able to fix bugs.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Getting the sources and building</title>

    <para>In the documents directory, you can find a buildguide, this guide
    explains how to get the sources from the CVS, how to get Kylix Open
    Edition and how to rebuild the sources. You can also rebuild XPde by using
    Ant, check out the build.xml file.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>CVS</title>

    <para>To submit your changes and collaborate with other members in this
    project, you will need to use CVS, don&#39;t worry about that, it&#39;s a
    very simple system and if you have never used it, we bet you will think
    it&#39;s great. You can find all this information in the documents
    directory, on the CVS guide.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Resources</title>

    <para>As a team we have a list of resources we use, for source code, for
    communication, etc:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Main Page (http://www.xpde.com)</para>

        <para>This is the main page of the project, it&#39;s the central
        repository of resources and news, this must be your first stop</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Project Page (http://developer.berlios.de/projects/xpde)</para>

        <para>We host our project on BerliOS, the system they use it&#39;s the
        same than SourceForge, we only use their CVS server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>CVS repository (http://cvs.berlios.de/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/xpde/)</para>

        <para>To browse the source code, you can use the Browse CVS option at
        the project page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Bug tracking (http://bugs.xpde.com)</para>

        <para>This is the bug tracking tool we use, it&#39;s a Mantis, you
        will need to subscribe yourself to report bugs and also tell us to be
        updated as developer and be able to fix bugs</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ticketing (http://dcl.xpde.com)</para>

        <para>This is a system to manage work on a team, to send tickets to
        each other requesting for work, or simply a common place to setup
        things to do, right now it&#39;s not very useful due the current size
        of the team, but it will become very important in a near future.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>IRC Channel (irc://irc.freenode.net/xpde)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Forums (http://www.xpde.com/modules.php?name=Forums)</para>

        <para>Users can post their questions here, right now post is only
        allowed to registered users, maybe this change in a future. At the
        bottom you can find a private forum for the team, contact with us to
        get the password.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>FAQ (http://www.xpde.com/modules.php?name=FAQ)</para>

        <para>Here you can find a FAQ, it&#39;s nice to read it to know what
        to answer in the forums to give support to users</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Team page (http://www.xpde.com/modules.php?name=Team)</para>

        <para>This is the XPde team, we are listed in joining order</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mailing List (mailto:development-subscribe@xpde.com)</para>

        <para>This is our main way to communicate, right now there is only one
        list, this will grow in the future</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Coding guidelines</title>

    <para>It is very important to use some coding guidelines when developing
    in a collaborative project like this, the code must be as clearer as
    possible and every member must be able to read it. We are not talking
    about design patterns, but a coding style to make all source code look the
    same. This guidelines are not closed, and we, as Delphi developers, we
    have a very similar coding style. All this is explained in a separate
    document, called coding guidelines, but it&#39;s not finished yet.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Form design</title>

    <para>In this project we have little space for innovation on form design,
    we have a model on Windows XP which we must follow to-the-pixel-point, but
    in any other case, where the Windows XP dialogs are not what we must use
    in Linux, we must follow some common rules. Also, this is nice to allow
    another team members to edit our forms. To let our forms integrate with
    the rest of the desktop and to react to user changes on desktop and
    appearance properties, we must use the XPstyle unit, a Kylix/Qt style
    which changes all the way our widgets look. Also we need to set the Scaled
    properties of all our forms to false and the ParentFont to true.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Document creation</title>

    <para>If you need to create documents to be shared with another members or
    published to the users, we are using DocBook as publishing platform, this
    system is based on XML and allows to write the document and publish it on
    many formats including PDF, HTML, PS, TXT, etc. You can also use XXE, from
    XMLMinds as editor, it&#39;s made in Java and provides CSS rendering for
    DocBook documents, so it&#39;s just like a word processor.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>License</title>

    <para>This project is GPL, this means all the code we write is under that
    license, you cannot join the team and develope source code under another
    license or use source code under a non-compatible license.</para>
  </sect1>
</article>