<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Build Guide</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>2002/11/19</date>

    <author>
      <surname>León</surname>

      <firstname>José</firstname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document explains how to build XPde from the sources on the
    CVS. It documents how to get the sources, where to get and install Kylix
    OE, which ProjectGroup to load and what packages to install in the IDE.
    It&#39;s very simple, just follow these steps and you could
    rebuild/modify/contribute to XPde.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Getting the sources</title>

    <para>To get the sources you will need a cvs client, it&#39;s included in
    most common Linux distributions, you can check it by typing cvs in the
    command prompt:</para>

    <programlisting>ttm@ttm:~&#62; cvs
Usage: cvs [cvs-options] command [command-options-and-arguments]
  where cvs-options are -q, -n, etc.
    (specify --help-options for a list of options)
  where command is add, admin, etc.
    (specify --help-commands for a list of commands
     or --help-synonyms for a list of command synonyms)
  where command-options-and-arguments depend on the specific command
    (specify -H followed by a command name for command-specific help)
  Specify --help to receive this message

The Concurrent Versions System (CVS) is a tool for version control.
For CVS updates and additional information, see
    the CVS home page at http://www.cvshome.org/ or
    Pascal Molli&#39;s CVS site at http://www.loria.fr/~molli/cvs-index.html
</programlisting>

    <para>If you don&#39;t have it, you can install the package from your
    Linux distro or browse to <olink>http://www.cvshome.org</olink>.</para>

    <para>To get the XPde sources, go to your home directory and type these
    commands:</para>

    <programlisting>cvs -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.xpde.berlios.de:/cvsroot/xpde login

cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.xpde.berlios.de:/cvsroot/xpde co xpde</programlisting>

    <para>The first comand will login into the server, if you are prompted for
    a password, just press enter. The second command will create a directory
    called xpde under your current directory and will download all the sources
    from the CVS server.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Installing Kylix OE</title>

    <para>Kylix OE is a down-sized version of Kylix Enterprise, it&#39;s free
    for download and allows only GPL development, so fits very well with this
    project. We will always try that XPde can be built using Kylix OE. You can
    get it from <olink>http://www.borland.com/products/downloads/download_kylix.html</olink>,
    at the time of writting, the version you need to download is Kylix 3 Open
    Edition, requires registration.</para>

    <para>After you download, just decompress the file you downloaded,
    probably a tar.gz, by using:</para>

    <programlisting>tar xvzf yourfilename.tar.gz</programlisting>

    <para>This will create a directory which holds the Kylix Open Setup,
    execute the installation and follow the steps.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Note: Installing Kylix OE as root is reported to cause
    problems, so it&#39;s better you install it as the user is going to use
    it.</emphasis></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Rebuilding the sources</title>

    <para>Rebuild the sources is easy, you just need to open a project group,
    install several packages on the IDE and select Project | Build All
    projects command from the Kylix menu. The ProjectGroup you need to open is
    located at ~/xpde/src/core/xpde/XPdePG.bpg</para>

    <para>At the time of writting, the projectgroup is composed of this
    projects:</para>

    <programlisting>bplXPCommon
bplXPRegistry
bplXPAPI
bplXPMenus
bplXPStyle
bplXPLocalizator
bplXPLocalizatorIDE
bplXPColorSelect
bplXPShellControls
bplXPCommctrls
taskmanager
networkstatus
networkproperties
appexec
bpldesk.so
XPwm
XPde</programlisting>

    <para>The output dir of all packages and applications is set to
    $(HOME)/xpde, this means that this directory must exist, or you will get
    errors when compiling.</para>

    <para>You will need to install all packages from bplXPCommon to
    bplXPCommctrls, you can do that, but right-clicking on the Project Manager
    and selecting the option Install. This will rebuild that package and will
    install it on the IDE. </para>

    <para>The projectgroup will grow and maybe this guide will be outdated
    between releases, so the rule here is &#34;You must install in the IDE all
    the packages from the first until you find an application&#34;.</para>

    <para>After you install all the needed packages, you can use the command
    Project | Build All Projects, this will rebuild the entire project. And
    that&#39;s all, to get it running, read the Install guide which explains
    how to install it.</para>
  </sect1>
</article>