<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Development plan 3.0</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>2002/10/15</date>

    <author>
      <surname>León</surname>

      <firstname>José</firstname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>Purpose</title>

    <para>The purpose of this project is to create a Windows XP desktop for
    the Linux/x86 operating system. This means that any feature not
    implemented on Windows XP is NOT going to be implemented on XPde, if you
    want, you can create a fork, there is no problem about that. The reason is
    I think there is no need for another desktop environment to compete with
    KDE and Gnome, this project is developed only to help Windows users to
    migrate Linux, nothing more.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>miniFAQ</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Q. Why are you using Kylix? It&#39;s not free!!!</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A. IMO, Kylix is the best Linux development tool created ever, I
        started my career using C++, and right now, in my job I use mainly
        PHP, but believe me, Kylix is not only a pascal based language,
        it&#39;s a full development platform with a powerful class library and
        a lightnning fast compiler. That&#39;s why I started this project with
        Kylix, because is the best tool (IMO) for this job. I know it&#39;s
        not free, but you can download Kylix Open Edition for free to develop
        GPL projects like this, I invite you to give it a try, we will take
        care this project is fully compilable with Kylix Open Edition.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Q. Is going to be ported to another systems?</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A. No</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Q. Why??!!!</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A. Because Kylix runs only on Linux/X86, it&#39;s not possible
        to port this program to another systems if Borland doesn&#39;t port
        Kylix first. And also, this project is focused on one thing, provide
        Linux &#34;Desktop&#34; users with Windows XP interface.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Q. Why don&#39;t you use FreePascal?</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A. IMO, FreePascal is not powerful enough to create this project
        in a reasonable time frame</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Q. Why don&#39;t you join fwm, qvwm, @#!wm??!! They
        are doing a great job! Look at this screenshots!</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A. Well, I have seen many window managers/desktops since I
        started with Linux, none of them can be compared with this project.
        I&#39;m not saying this project is best, I&#39;m saying it has a
        different purpose and the most important, a complete different
        technology.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Project</title>

    <para><remark>Note:All the code you can read below, must be read as
    pseudocode, is not intended to work and it&#39;s not tested at all,
    it&#39;s just a guideline to future development.</remark></para>

    <para><remark>Note: Before start a task, we must stop and think about it,
    what is the best way to implement it, how are we going to divide the
    development and so on, this development plan only provide the basics for
    the development, is not an in-depth analysis.</remark></para>

    <para>This project is divided in several subprojects, and each one is a
    project by itself:</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Controls and Components</title>

      <para>A project like this requires total control over the way widgets
      draw and behave, some things can be done by tweaking Kylix Qt interface
      at low level, but there are another ones that require a new
      control/component, this is the initial list of components we must
      create:</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>XPShell</title>

        <para>This is the core of the project, it is responsible to load the
        desktop, the taskbar and the window manager as packages and implement
        the XPToolsAPI interface to allow each part interact with the desktop.
        Also, applets will be packages that will use the XPToolsAPI to
        customize the several aspects of the desktop. This will require two
        things:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Reestructure the current environment to be organized in
            loadable packages instead of single executables</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Create good quality and fault tolerant code, a general
            exception manager is required to log exceptions and allow users
            send us feedback.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>XPToolsAPI</title>

        <para>This is the API available to every part of the desktop, with
        this API, every module will be able to, for example, create shortcuts,
        change the desktop preferences, get information about desktop size,
        etc. It will be growing as the project grows and it must be designed
        in a modular way, separating similar tasks by smaller interfaces.
        Basically must provide most of the system functions you can find on
        the Windows API.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>XPStyle</title>

        <para>Qt style to draw widgets in the same way XP does, this style
        must extract all the paint information (colors, fonts, etc) from the
        registry to be shared among all the programs and to allow external
        configuration through themes/configuration dialogs. It must support
        third-party styles working this way:</para>

        <para>A style would be a compiled package, this package contain an
        object which implements IXPStyle interface, in the initialization of
        the package, it must register the style through the XPToolsAPI to
        indicate is available to the system. At first, the styles will be
        binary based, but as goodie, we can provide a style that reads an XML
        file with drawing operations to perform. Metacity themes can be the
        base to work on.</para>

        <para>Example:</para>

        <programlisting>IXPStyle=interface
   [&#39;{88F313AD-73E0-D611-98A9-000244219999}&#39;]
   procedure Configure;
   procedure Draw3dRect(const ARect:TRect);
   procedure Draw3dLine(const p1,p2:TPoint);
   procedure DrawButton(ACanvas:TCanvas;AButton:TObject);
   procedure DrawMenuItem(ACanvas:TCanvas;AItem:TMenuItem);
   .......
   .......
   .......
end;

TMyStyle=class(TInterfacedObject, IXPStyle)
   //Here goes all the methods!!
end;

initialization
   XPToolsAPI.registerStyle(&#39;MyStyle&#39;, TMyStyle.create);</programlisting>

        <para>The first style to be created must be the XP classic style and
        the second the Luna XP style. Probably styles could be created with
        Kylix C++, it would be nice to provide samples of both to encourage
        theme designers create more. As a goodie, we can create a style which
        reads from an XML file, operations to perform on each drawing method.
        As a super-super-goodie, we can incorporate interfaces to create those
        themes using perl, php, python, etc, etc, etc.... ;-)</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>ShellTreeView &#38; ShellListView &#38; ShellCombobox</title>

        <para>These controls are needed for the FileManager, for the Dialogs,
        and for the Desktop itself, the goal is to provide the same
        functionality that the Windows ones, shellicons, drag&#38;drop
        capabilities, edit/cut/copy/paste/delete operations, multiselection,
        etc. All the information about icons must be extracted from the
        registry to be shared among all the programs. Each item could be right
        clicked and must show a popup with the right operations to perform.
        That operations will be stored on the registry and the XPde compatible
        software could get profit from that (Zip extractors, Text editors,
        etc). The ShellListView must be able to have a clientrect property to
        simulate the space are going to use the tasksbars. The shellcombobox
        is just a combo with the ability to show the system items (My
        Documents, My Computer, and so on).</para>

        <para>Before starting create this project we must define what is the
        hierarchy of items (real and virtual) a user can explore. For example,
        My Computer is not a real item, but My Documents it is, but a special
        one, Network is an item which extracts all it&#39;s information from a
        virtual file system. This must be designed carefully before start this
        development. So all shell controls must be designed thinking on a
        virtual file system, not in a file based file system, these components
        will be the core part of the File Explorer. The XPToolsAPI could be
        used to register new file systems to extend the explorer and dialogs
        at the same time.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>OutlookBar</title>

        <para>A bar to show elements/tabs like Outlook, very useful for
        Dialogs or for an Outlook clone, it would be good to look for any
        freeware Delphi component to see if we can get some starting code.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Open/Save/Picture Dialog</title>

        <para>Dialogs based on ShellListView and OutlookBar.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>BrowseDialog</title>

        <para>Dialog to browse for a directory.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>XPMainMenu &#38; XPPopupMenu</title>

        <para>Menu components to draw/behave as XP and the most important, to
        integrate XP dissolving and fading effects. The PopupMenu must be able
        to create a menu like the XP start menu (multicolumn, custom items,
        etc) and each menu item must have the ability to be right clicked to
        show its properties menu.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>XPTaskbar</title>

        <para>This component must be able to behave as a taskbar and must be
        able to work on any position (bottom, left, top, right). This
        component must be able to hold several &#34;zones&#34;, each zone can
        be another control, for example an starbutton, a toolbar to hold
        active tasks, tray icon zone, etc. This component doesn&#39;t defines
        zones by itself, it&#39;s just a container with some common taskbar
        properties (align, always on top, auto-hide, etc).</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Desktop</title>

      <para>This project will use a ShellListView to show the user desktop
      directory contents and allow them to interact with the desktop items
      (files, folders, shortcuts, system items). It will also use the
      XPPopupMenu component to show a list of common operations. It must
      design and implement an interface called IXPDesktop to allow other
      modules interact with it.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Window Manager &#38; Taskbar</title>

      <para>Seems two very different tasks, but in fact, are very similar, the
      Window Manager is responsible to &#34;map&#34; each client window inside
      a frame to be moved/resized and the taskbar is responsible to
      &#34;map&#34; each client window inside it to allow the user change the
      active tasks, that&#39;s why are same program. It must design and
      implement two interfaces called IXPWindowManager and IXPTaskbar to allow
      other modules interact with it.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Window Manager</title>

        <para>The Window Manager will be based on Metacity code (until further
        change) because Metacity code it&#39;s based on Gtk and performs
        little low level operations, so the code is very similar to the one we
        must write, little Xlib stuff and a lot of high level code. We must
        first create a version which reproduces the classic XP windows
        interface in a native way, after that, we must incorporate themes.
        This is done this way to let the classic theme be the fastest because
        it will be native code and after that add theme support through XML or
        any other way. Before start this task, we need to make a list of all
        the features this Window Manager must have.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Taskbar</title>

        <para>This part will use the XPTaskbar component. It will create a
        Start button Zone, a Quick Launch zone, a Tasks zone, and a Trayicon
        zone, it must be also able to add more zones like XP does (folders,
        etc). It will also create the Start menu based on the XPPopupMenu
        component, it will be responsible to read user&#39;s Start Menu
        directory recursively searching for elements (folders, links, files),
        etc. Also it will be responsible to hold the tray icon zone with the
        system clock and allow to configure it. The taskbar can be configured
        through a dialog and those settings will be stored on the registry.
        Before start this task, we need to make a list of all the features
        this Taskbar must have.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>File Manager &#38; Internet Browser</title>

      <para>This two tasks are the same program, an Internet Browser is just a
      File Manager module to browse Internet, so the File Manager must be
      designed as a framework to hold modules to show a file system (nfs, smb,
      ftp, webdav, zip, etc) or custom content (internet, special dirs, etc).
      Basically it will use the Shell components to build a standard file
      manager and after that it will start to load special modules to handle
      smb, nfs, zip, ftp, webdav, internet, special dirs, and so on.</para>

      <para>(here we must define the format of the virtual filesystem
      interface, it must be very similar to ftp (getdircontents,
      getcurrentdir, delete, etc))</para>

      <para>Modules to create:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>nfs, a module to explore and interact with the Linux network</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>smb, a module to explore and interact with the SMB newtwork</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ftp, a module to explore and interact with the ftp network</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>zip, a module to explore and interact with zip files</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>dav, a module to explore and interact with webdav servers</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>internet, a module to explore internet, must be based on an
          existent browser (ie Mozilla or another) and must encapsulate the
          browser allowing future changes in the interface</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>specialdirs, this module must be able to read a hidden file on
          each dir to get user preferences about a directory, even load
          another modules, for example, to prevent a user to enter a system
          dir, or to show the fonts dir, or even to show control panel items.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All modules will have interfaces available to interact with
          the File Manager (create buttons, create toolbars, menu items,
          status bars)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Control Panel</title>

      <para>Control Panel is not a task by itself, it&#39;s just a special dir
      which will hold several .cpl files, those files are executables to
      control several aspects of the environment, each applet can have
      different parts on it, for example, change screen resolution or select
      the current theme.</para>

      <para>Applets to create:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Accesibility</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add Hardware</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add or Remove Programs</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Administrative Tools</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Date and Time</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Display</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Folder Options</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fonts</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Game Controllers</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Internet Options</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Keyboard</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Mouse</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Network Connections</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Phone and Modem Options</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Power Options</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Printers and Faxes</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Regional and Language Options</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Scanners and Cameras</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Scheduled Tasks</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sounds and Audio Devices</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Speech</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>System</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Taskbar and Start Menu</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>User Accounts</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Many of these applets will depend of the Linux distribution, so I
      think we will need to create several versions for each Linux
      distribution, we will see.</para>

      <para>The icon from the applet will be extracted from a file with the
      same name but with extension .png (another dimensions will be supported
      also), for example:</para>

      <programlisting>desk.cpl
desk_48x48.png
desk_32x32.png
desk_16x16.png</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Themes</title>

      <para>A theme will be composed by:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Visual Style</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Window Manager Decorations</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>System Icons</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>System Sounds</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>System Cursors</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Desktop Background</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Tools</title>

      <para>This project is responsible to provide the applications installed
      by default by Windows XP, each project must be considered a separate
      project and must be analyzed before start, here it&#39;s the list:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Accessories</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Accessibility</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Accessibility Wizard</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Magnifier</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Narrator</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>On-Screen Keyboard</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Utility Manager</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Communications</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>HyperTerminal</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Network Connections</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Network Setup Wizard</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>New Connection Wizard</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Remote Desktop Connection</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Entertainment</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Sound Recorder</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Volume Control</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Media Player</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>System Tools</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Backup</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Character Map</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Disk Cleanup</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Disk Defragmenter</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Files and Settings Transfer Wizard</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Scheduled Tasks</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>System Information</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>System restore</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Address Book</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Calculator</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Command Prompt</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Notepad</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Paint</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Tour XPde</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>WordPad</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Of course, not all can be created or can work the same, but we
      must try to create new applications or reuse existing ones. A priority
      must be set here to develop first the most needed ones, like Notepad.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Project Timeline</title>

    <para>When a project like this starts, it&#39;s very strange to get a lot
    of developers involved with it, and also Kylix is not the most used Linux
    development tool, so we must prioritize the most attractive features over
    the most functional ones, this will make more developers join, because
    they will see the development progress. So here is my proposed time lime,
    feel free to send me any comment and suggestion:</para>

    <para>The graphic design is a task is going to last all the project,
    that&#39;s why it&#39;s not included on any release, basically is composed
    by two main areas:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Icon Design: Create all kind of icons needed for the desktop and
        programs</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Graphic Design: Create all images needed for the desktop and
        programs</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The translation process must be the last task to be performed before
    a release, so the work on this project must follow these basic steps:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Develop</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Translation and Test</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fix bugs</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Release</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>We must have clear the goals of each release, we must make more
    stable the current code before start develop features of the next release.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>XPde 0.2</title>

      <para>I think we must give first the ability to manage the files, and a
      File Manager is a key piece of an environment, when this part is
      finished, we could post a lot of new screenshots:<itemizedlist><listitem><para>XPShell
      &#38; XPToolsAPI</para></listitem><listitem><para>ShellTreeView &#38;
      ShellListView &#38; ShellCombobox</para></listitem><listitem><para>File
      Manager</para></listitem></itemizedlist>To test the ShellListView
      component and to announce the desktop is full working, let&#39;s finish
      the desktop:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Desktop</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To make all widgets look as Windows XP and to allow create
      applications with XP look, let&#39;s finish the XPStyle</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>XPStyle</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To remove dependencies of Metacity, to allow window manager
      integration with the desktop and full productivity with the environment:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Window Manager</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XPTaskbar</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Taskbar</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To allow configure the most common settings, finish this desktop
      applets:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Taskbar and Start Menu</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>User Accounts</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Date and Time</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Display</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Regional and Language Options (this will be also used to
          change the language of the environment)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>XPde 0.3</title>

      <para>To start finishing most common user operations:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Internet Browser</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>nfs module</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>smb module</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>specialdirs modules</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Internet Options applet</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To give all applications complete Windows XP interface:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>OutlookBar</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open/Save/Picture Dialog</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>BrowseDialog</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To include the most used tools:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Address Book</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Calculator</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Command Prompt</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Notepad</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Paint</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>WordPad</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>XPde 0.4</title>

      <para>To include all Windows XP effects:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>XPMainMenu &#38; XPPopupMenu</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To release the screenshots everybody will be waiting:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Theme engine</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Design LunaXP theme</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To give more exploring capabilities:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>ftp module</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>zip module</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>dav module</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To add more applets to the control panel:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Folder Options</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fonts</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Keyboard</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Mouse</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Volume Control</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>XPde 1.0</title>

      <para>To add something that could be useful to novice users, but is
      dependant from the Linux distribution:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Network Connections</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Network Setup Wizard</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>New Connection Wizard</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To add another really used tool:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Media Player (based on mplayer??)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>And finally, two months or so in beta phase, to test, bug fixing,
      releasing...</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The rest</title>

      <para>The rest of tasks must be made in no special order, I think is too
      early to plan this.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Team</title>

    <para>Each member of the development team will have one function (or
    more), these are the positions to fill:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Core developer</para>

        <para>Someone fully committed to the project, with at least 10 hours
        free per week ;-)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Project Manager</para>

        <para>Someone willing to coordinate a team of developers and to be
        responsible of some task</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Developer</para>

        <para>Someone willing to collaborate writting code</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Doc Writer</para>

        <para>Someone willing to write documentation (good english knowledge
        required)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Translator</para>

        <para>Someone willing to translate software/documentation to another
        language</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tester</para>

        <para>Someone willing to become part of the QA team</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Support Manager</para>

        <para>Someone willing to support users on forums, mail lists,
        newsgroups and so on</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Graphic Designer</para>

        <para>Someone willing to give a corporate image to the project by
        designing icons, graphics, etc</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Content Writer</para>

        <para>Someone willing to evangelize the use of the environment by
        writting technical reviews, articles, or to be an editor on the
        website</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Release Manager</para>

        <para>Someone reponsible to stick together all the project pieces to
        create a release, coordinate distribution, mirroring, etc</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Each member will get an *****@xpde.com pop address to be recognized
    as a member of the team and to be used exclusively for the development,
    unauthorized use could lead to get out of the team.</para>

    <para>The following tools will be used:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Kylix 3 (Delphi)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>CVS to store sources and allow concurrent development</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DocBook to create documentation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>XXE (http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/), the best and easiest
        XML editor I know (developed in Java)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DCL (http://dcl.sourceforge.net), a ticketing software to manage
        group work</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mantis (http://mantisbt.sourceforce.net), a really good
        bugtracking software</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Kylix documentor (still to find a good one, it must be ala
        doc-o-matic style (http://www.doc-o-matic.com/))</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Kylix code formatter (still to find a good one) to make all
        sources look the same style</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Kylix localizator (currently in development)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The following services has been setup and must be mantained:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Bugtracking (http://bugs.xpde.com)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ticketing (http://dcl.xpde.com)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>IRC Channel (irc://irc.freenode.net/xpde)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mail list (mailto:development-subscribe@xpde.com)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Forums (http://www.xpde.com/modules.php?name=Forums)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>FAQ (http://www.xpde.com/modules.php?name=FAQ)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>CVS server (cvs.xpde.berlios.de)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The following services will be available in the future:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Newsgroup(s)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The coding guidelines must be released in short and to join the
    group, please, e-mail to info@xpde.com telling why do you want to become
    part of this project and what you want to do. If you think you don&#39;t
    know enough Kylix or your contribution is very small, don&#39;t hesitate
    to send me a mail, maybe your help is more valuable than you think.</para>

    <para>Regards.</para>
  </sect1>
</article>